We received a call that a minor was kidnapped.
刚才有人报警说有未成年被诱拐
Would you mind coming to the station?
能否跟我到警察局走一趟？
Ms. Hijiri Suenaga.
末永圣小姐
You are suspected of kidnapping a minor.
你涉嫌诱拐未成年
Kidnap?
诱拐？
This has to be a misunderstanding.
不是 这其中一定有误会
We just met and talked.
我们只是碰到面在聊天
His parent has lodged a complaint.
他的家长控诉你诱拐
If this continues, I will have to take legal action.
如果你继续下去 我将采取法律行动
If I could speak with Ms. Kuroiwa, I'm sure I could clear this up.
如果能让我跟黑岩小姐谈谈 我一定能解开误会…
Not until we're finished talking here.
必须等到侦讯结束之后
I'm the one who led her around.
是我带走老师
If she sees you now…!
如果她现在见到你的话…
My mother was about to catch us together.
因为我怕被妈妈看见我们在一起
That's why I did.
所以我才会这样做
He's still a minor.
他还是未成年
Kidnapping a minor carries a sentence of three months to seven years.
诱拐未成年会处以三个月以上 七年以下的有期徒刑
If there's sexual misconduct, that's one to ten years of prison.
如果还有猥亵目的 将被判处一年以上 十年以下的监禁
We
我们
We just…
我们只是…
By the way, even if a minor consented,
顺带一提 即便未成年本人同意
if it goes against their guardian's wishes,
但违反其监护人意愿的话
it's considered a crime.
罪名仍会成立
Everyone always claims it's consensual.
每个人都说这是双方自愿的
I communicated the severity of the situation.
我已经告诉她严重性了
However, I doubt this case can be taken any further.
不过应该无法成立罪名
I see.
这样啊
If you are not happy with this, there are other measures you may take.
如果你不满意 也能想想别的方法
Akira.
阿晶
Where is Ms. Suenaga?
老师呢？
Why did you do this?
你为什么要这样？
If she gets charged with anything--
如果她被起诉的话…
Don't worry, she can go home once they're done.
别担心 问完话就会让她回去
It's not her fault.
不是老师的错
-I'm the one-- -Yes.
-是我… -是的
You're the one who was pulling her out of there.
是你拉着她逃跑
What?
什么？
It's your fault this happened.
会变成这样都是你的错
I warned her there would be no next time.
我警告过她不能再有下一次
But she met you in secret.
可是她却偷偷去见你
She's lost my trust and I'll hold her accountable.
我不能再相信她 也会让她负上责任
-I'm the one responsible. -You're a minor.
-我才是应该被究责 -你还未成年
You can't take responsibility.
你没办法负责
Your phone.
你的手机
Give me your phone.
手机给我
I'm deleting her number.
我要删掉她的电话号码
You'll only make it worse for her.
你只会让她的情况更糟糕
Is that what you want?
那样好吗？
-Can you take Akira home? -Yes.
-你能先送阿晶回去吗？ -好
Boss, I know you're worried,
社长 我知道你很担心
but if you push too hard, it'll have the opposite effect.
但如果态度过度强硬 反而会造成反效果
HIJIRI
（小圣）
Akira!
阿晶！
DELETE
（删除）
DELETED
（已删除）
It's for the best.
这样就好了
Ms. Kuroiwa, I'm sorry.
黑岩小姐 对不起
Um, I'm the one who approached him.
我跑去找黑岩同学
But we weren't trying to run away together.
可是我没有要诱拐他或逃跑
Why don't we talk tomorrow instead.
这里不方便说话 有事明天再谈吧
Here at one o'clock.
一点在这里会面
Okay.
我明白了
Mom?
妈妈？
-How? -This was in your room.
-你怎么… -这个在你房间
Imagine my surprise,
想想我有多惊讶
since I thought you were going to move back home with us…
我本以为你会搬回到家里来…
I didn't want to burden you any more.
我不能再给你们添麻烦
You were planning to meet with that boy here?
你打算在这里跟那孩子见面吗？
Ms. Kuroiwa just called me.
刚才黑岩小姐打给我
The police were involved?
连警察都介入了？
I'm going to talk with Ms. Kuroiwa tomorrow.
明天我会跟黑岩小姐谈
I'm sure if I just explain, she'll--
只要解释清楚为什么会这样 她就会…
Do whatever you want.
你想怎样就怎样吧
I can't believe you.
我真不敢相信
You're on your own now.
以后你就自己想办法吧
TOKYO NATIONAL UNIVERSITY APPLICATION
（东京国立大学 入学申请书）
Are you Hijiri Suenaga?
你是末永圣小姐吗？
Yes?
是
My name is Isogai, and I'm an attorney.
我是矶贝 是一名律师
I'm here to represent Ms. Kuroiwa.
我今天是以 黑岩小姐的代理人身分与你见面
CLAIRE SOGO LAW OFFICE
（克莱尔综合法律事务所）
A settlement?
和解？
After some deliberation, Ms. Kuroiwa is willing to forego
黑岩小姐经过深思后
escalating the matter to the police or the school board.
这次不打算向警方提出告诉 或通报教育委员会
However, it's under the condition that you sign this legal agreement.
只不过条件是要请你在契约书上签名
Agreement?
契约书？
"I Hijiri Suenaga will sever all communication with Akira Kuroiwa.
“本人 末永圣 往后将会与黑岩晶中断一切联系
Should I break any of these conditions,
若本人违反以下任何条件
I will pay a compensation fee of five million yen to Aiko Kuroiwa
即刻支付五百万圆 给黑岩爱子作为赔偿金
for violating her custodial rights.
基于侵害她的监护权为由
No matter the consequences I face,
无论受到何种处分
I agree that I will make no object to this stipulation."
都不会对此提出异议”
AIKO KUROIWA, MOTHER OF AKIRA KUROIWA
（黑岩晶的母亲 黑岩爱子）
Could I speak to Ms. Kuroiwa directly?
我能跟黑岩小姐见一面吗？
She does not wish to see you.
她说不想跟你见面
You have one week, I shall await your call.
期限是一周 我静候你的答复
AGREEMENT
（契约书）
I'll submit this.
我会提交这个
UNIVERSITY APPLICATION
（大学入学申请书）
I'll do what you say
我会听你的话
and focus on my exams.
专心备考
So please promise to consider Ms. Suenaga someday--
所以 请答应我将来考虑老师…
Once this is over.
等这结束吧
Just focus on your exams right now,
总之你现在专心考试
then we'll talk.
其他之后再说
Okay.
我知道了
You have one week, I shall await your call.
期限是一周 我静候你的答复
Ms. Chizuru?
千鹤小姐？
Here, your belongings that were left at the school.
这个 是你留在教职员室的私人物品
Thank you.
谢谢你
I knew it.
我就知道
Of course it didn't work out.
你们果然不可能顺利的
Everyone was against it, but you two were infatuated.
被众人反对 沈醉在两人世界
This is the result.
结果就是这样
You did it to yourself.
自作自受
I have the worst mentee!
真的是个差劲的后辈！
Eat, sleep, talk.
吃饭 睡觉 说话
Whenever you feel like you can't take it anymore…
每当你觉得已经撑不下去了…
Just eat, sleep,
就去吃饭 睡觉
and talk to someone.
跟别人聊聊
If you have nobody to talk to, you can call me.
若是没有人能说话就打给我
I'll swing by if I'm free.
我有空就会过来
Okay.
好
Now stop crying.
别哭啦
You are such a crier.
真是爱哭鬼
Fine, cry it out.
好啦 哭吧
Cry all you want.
都哭出来吧
Do whatever you want.
你想怎样就怎样吧
I can't believe you.
我真不敢相信
I will have to take legal action.
我将采取法律行动
I want to be by your side.
我想陪在老师身边
Now until forever.
从现在直到永远
TOKYO
（东京）
Why are you running away like I have the plague or something?
干嘛急着走啊？好像我是衰神一样
Not exactly the plague.
不能说是衰神
More like,
更像是
some gross obsessed guy who's not over his ex.
放不下前任的恶心纠缠男
Then come with me.
那你跟我走吧
I'm going to Singapore.
我会去新加坡
I'm sorry. I can't go with you.
对不起 我不能跟你走
I was worried about Hijiri.
我是担心圣
No, your pride was hurt.
不 你只是被伤到了自尊心
Because for once in your life, things didn't go your way.
这是你活到现在 第一次遇到事情不顺心
I guess I've got no right to criticize you.
不过我也没资格说别人
Hijiri got into it with the kid's mom,
圣好像跟那孩子的妈妈起了争执
and it's a big deal.
事情闹得很大
What?
什么？
So the two of them…?
那他们现在…
Something happened with Hijiri, right?
黑岩 你跟小圣发生了什么 是吧？
-Crap, that sucks! -Yeah.
-糟糕 果然惨爆了！ -是啊
First there's the thing with Hijiri, and you also pissed off your old lady.
先是小圣的事 然后还惹恼了你妈
That's a terrible combo right there!
跟薯条配咖啡一样糟啊！
Hey.
喂
I wonder what becoming an adult means.
变成大人到底是怎样呢？
Anyway, I just want to go to university to give Mom peace of mind,
总之我现在要先上大学让我妈放心
so she'll accept Ms. Suenaga.
让她接受老师
I'm not giving up until she does.
在那之前我绝不放弃
Well, I always thought
那个 我一直在想
it'd be nice if you ended up together.
你们若能在一起就好了
Really?
真的？
I may not look it, but I love true romance!
别看我这样 我可是浪漫主义者喔！
Cut it out! What's wrong with you!
住手！干嘛啦！
Let's go Kuroiwa, the man who cannot be stopped!
黑岩 不屈服的男人 加油！
Kuroiwa, is the man!
黑岩 不屈服的男人…
-Okay, that's enough. -Sorry.
-好了 够了啦 -抱歉
MS. HARAGUCHI
（原口小姐）
I bought this body cream in New York.
这是在纽约买的润肤霜
And I'm regifting this soup set.
还有抱歉 这个汤包组是别人送的
This is detergent, and here's an electric blanket.
这是洗洁精 还有这个电热毯
Thank you, but why are you giving me all this?
谢谢你 但是为什么送我这些？
This hardly makes up for it,
虽说这些东西都不足以表达歉意
but my meddling got you in trouble with his mother.
但都怪我太鸡婆 害你被他妈妈…
Please, it was my own decision.
拜托 那是我自己决定去的
What about eloping?
你们要不干脆私奔吧？
I have friends who run a hostel for riders.
我有认识一对夫妻在经营骑士民宿
Riders?
骑士？
Not the super heroes. Bikers and cyclists.
不是会变身的那种假面骑士喔 是机车和脚踏车骑士
I think they were looking for workers.
我想他们正在招募服务生
I guess you can't.
我想你不行吧
I know you're dealing with a lot.
抱歉 我知道你现在很多事要烦
I was told
我被告知
that I have to promise
必须承诺
never to see Kuroiwa again.
以后不会再跟黑岩见面
They want me to sign an agreement.
叫我在契约书上签名
You mean they took legal action?
对方采取法律途径吗？
I told myself that I wouldn't lie about my feelings anymore.
我告诉自己不要再欺瞒自己的心意
What do I do?
我该怎么做？
What's best for everyone?
怎样才是对大家好的？
I'm so lost.
我完全没有头绪
Well,
这个
that goes for everyone.
任谁都一样
Sorry, one sec.
抱歉 失陪一下
Ms. Haraguchi! Are you okay?
原口小姐！你还好吗？
-Please call an ambulance. -Okay.
-麻烦帮我叫救护车 -是
Are you okay, Ms. Haraguchi?
你还好吗 原口小姐？
LOC is 200, blood pressure 169 over 98.
清醒程度200 血压169 98
Pulse is 125, saturation is 94 percent.
脉搏125 血氧量94%
Let's hurry, make way!
快点 让开！
I'm sorry, could you see if she has any insurance information or hospital card?
抱歉 能麻烦你找找她 是否有任何保险信息或健保卡吗？
Of course.
好的
MATERNITY JOURNAL
（母子健康日志）
How is she?
她怎么了？
She's being treated.
还在治疗
They're running other tests as well.
也要做其他检查以防万一
What tests?
什么检查？
MATERNITY JOURNAL
（母子健康日志）
Here.
这个
She's three months pregnant.
她怀孕三个月了
You didn't know?
你不知道吗？
Not at all.
完全不知道
Totally clueless.
什么都不知道
Why did she not…?
原口小姐为什么不说…
We just finished her examination.
检查刚刚结束了
Her CT and MRI results were cleared.
断层扫描跟核磁共振结果都没问题
But her blood pressure isn't stabilizing. We'll keep her here for observation.
但血压尚未稳定 谨慎起见 还是要住院观察几日
Ms. Haraguchi.
原口小姐
How are you feeling?
觉得怎么样？
I brought you a change of clothing.
我先帮你带了些换洗衣物
Oh, Hijiri.
哦 是小圣啊
Thanks, you didn't need to.
谢谢 不用这样劳烦你的
-I was just about to leave. -To go where?
-我刚好要出去 -要去哪里？
Home, and then work.
先回家一趟后直接去公司
You should be resting.
你还要静养啊
I need to wrap this work up.
我得把这项工作收尾
I'll be back tonight though.
没事的 晚上我会回来
Ms. Haraguchi!
原口小姐！
-You should stay. -I'll be fine.
-你还是待在医院吧 -我没事啦
-This is a crucial-- -Yes, it's a crucial project.
-现在是重要… -没错 是很重要的计划
It's an ODA for Africa.
有关非洲政府开发协助
-A big dam-- -Which is more important?
-大型水坝 -哪一个比较重要？
There's a baby inside you.
你有宝宝了
I was surprised at first,
虽然刚听到时很震惊
but I'm happy.
可是我很高兴
This is a blessing.
这是很幸福的事
Nothing should be more important!
没有事情比这更重要！
Please go back and rest.
请回去好好静养
Yes, Ms. Suenaga.
是 老师
I decided.
我决定了
I'll become a mother.
我要成为母亲
I'll raise them on my own.
我要独自生下孩子养育他
I made up my mind just now.
我刚刚下定决心了
Thanks to you.
托你的福
Congratulations.
恭喜你
But what about Shotaro?
胜太郎那边呢？
I gave it some thought as well.
我也像你一样仔细思考过
What would be best for everyone, just like you did.
怎样才是对大家好的 像你那样
What is the right answer?
怎么做才是正确答案？
But then I realized something.
可是我发现
There is no right answer.
没有什么正确解答
It's unknowable.
那是未知的
That's why
因此
you have to find your own right answer.
要找出属于自己的正解
As I move forward on my own,
当我独自前行时
I have faith the answer is ahead.
我相信答案就在前方
NOW HIRING
（现正招募）
WINTER LECTURE APPLICATION
（冬季课程报名表）
Kuroiwa?
黑岩
Thought that was you! I heard a lot happened.
果然是你！听说你发生了很多事
I heard from Kokonoe that you and…
我听九重说了 你跟…
Kuroiwa.
黑岩
-Thought you were a target. -Ow.
-还以为是标靶呢 -噢
Let's both do our best.
我们彼此都加油吧
Let's go.
走吧
-Did you study for the vocab test? -No.
-你有背今天要考的单字吗？ -我没背
-Ms. Suenaga. -Yes?
-末永小姐 -是
-Can you get this to Takahashi? -Yes.
-能帮我把这个送去给高桥吗？ -好
Thanks.
谢咯
You have one week, I shall await your call.
期限是一周 我静候你的答复
Has she contacted you?
她联络你了吗？
No.
没有
She hasn't reached out?
她没有主动联系你？
The deadline is tomorrow.
回复期限是明天
Do you think she's not planning on signing the agreement?
她该不会不打算签名吧？
If she doesn't, we will bring formal charges to the police.
她不签的话 我们会正式向警方提出告诉
I hate to cause all this trouble right before exams.
在考试前 我不想把事情闹大
Yes, that is what this agreement is for.
是 也是为此才准备了契约书
I will go visit her directly tomorrow.
明天我会直接去拜访她
-She will promise never to-- -Agreement?
-请她承诺往后别再… -契约书？
-Akira. -What is this?
-阿晶 -那是什么意思？
-What about your test? -The hell is this!
-模拟考呢？ -这是什么东西！
Akira!
阿晶！
You said you'd think about Ms. Suenaga after my exams!
你说考完试就会考虑老师的事！
That's why I've--
所以我才…
Think about what? You making the same mistake again?
考虑什么？ 你又要重复一样的错吗？
You never told me about any agreement!
我没听你提过什么契约书！
Akira, please calm down.
阿晶 请冷静听我说
Who the hell are you? What did you do to Ms. Suenaga!
你谁啊？你对老师做了什么！
Stop it, Akira!
住手 阿晶！
You may not understand now, but you will someday!
就算你现在不理解 总有一天会明白！
Why I'm going this far.
为什么我要做到这个地步
That I'm doing this so you can have a proper childhood!
我这样做 是为了让你有一个正常的童年！
Akira.
阿晶
Stop!
给我站住！
AGREEMENT
（契约书）
SIGNATURE
（签名）
Turn left after that diner.
过那间家庭餐厅后左转
There is no right answer.
没有什么正确解答
You have to find your own right answer.
要找出属于自己的正解
Yes?
是
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
It's me.
是我
You're there aren't you?
你在吧？
Please open the door.
请开门吧
I want to see you,
我想见你
to hear your voice.
想听你的声音
Please, Ms. Suenaga.
拜托了 老师
Excuse me.
不好意思
May I come in?
我可以进去吗？
-Yes. -Excuse me.
-是的 -不好意思
I'm sorry for dropping by.
突然跑来真是抱歉
I'm here about that.
我是为了那件事来的
I was just about to call you.
我也正好要打给你
I'm sorry for asking you to meet me today.
真是抱歉 今日特意请你出面
I wanted to speak with you properly--
我想跟你好好谈一谈
The agreement?
契约书呢？
Kuroiwa came to see me last night.
黑岩同学昨晚来见我了
He said he wanted to see me.
他说他想要见我
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
I don't care what anyone says.
我不管谁说什么
As long as I have you.
我只要有老师
So please…
所以求求你…
I didn't open the door.
我没有开门
He eventually left.
后来他就走了
I was planning to tell you the following.
我本来打算这样告诉你
Our resolve is strong, we can wait.
我们的决心很坚定 我们能等待
To please trust us.
请你相信我们
But Kuroiwa is still 18.
但是黑岩同学他果然还只是十八岁
A dangerous age,
非常危险的年纪
easily swayed by emotion.
容易被情绪冲昏头
He will regress,
无法前进
back to the past.
驻足在过去
I can now painfully understand
我非常能体会
your worry.
你担心黑岩同学的心情
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
What is most important to your son
对你儿子来说最重要的
is his future.
是他的未来
No matter how strongly we felt, we should have left it buried.
无论我们的感觉有多强烈 我们都应该把它埋在心底
If I truly cared for him, there was so much I should've given him.
如果我真心为他着想就应该给予他
Like time, distance, and potential.
像时间 距离和可能性
That was my responsibility as an adult.
这些明明是大人的责任
But I failed.
我却没做到
For that,
为此
I offer my apology.
我诚挚地向你致歉
I will never see him again.
我不会再与他见面
Please tell
也请帮我转告
Kuroiwa that for me.
黑岩同学
Excuse me.
不好意思
You're down here early.
这么早就下来啦
Usually, you never come when I call you.
以前不管我怎么叫 你都不下来
Get the soy sauce out.
酱油拿出来
So what happened?
老师呢？
Did you see her today?
你今天见到她了吗？
Please.
拜托你
Tell me.
告诉我
AGREEMENT
（契约书）
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
This was her answer.
这就是老师的回答
Do you understand, Akira?
你懂吗 阿晶？
PROMISE NOT TO MAKE CONTACT OF ANY KIND.
（承诺不会以任何方式 再与对方联络）
Understand why this happened?
事情为什么会变这样？
Understand what she felt
老师到底是用什么心情
when signing this.
签了名
What is it you can do?
你能做些什么？
How will you meet her sacrifice?
对于她的付出 你能如何回报？
Think about that, Akira.
你自己想清楚 阿晶
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
Thank you for this food.
我开动了
-Thank you. -Please come again.
-谢谢光临 -欢迎再来
You can clock out now.
末永小姐 你可以下班了
You've done such a great job.
你真是能干
Would you like to work full time?
你要不要当正式员工？
Thank you.
谢谢你
But there's something else I'm considering right now.
不过我另有打算
NATIONAL JAPANESE LANGUAGE JSL EDUCATORS
（国际日文协会海外教育队）
HIRING JAPANESE LANGUAGE TEACHERS
（日文老师招募中）
If it isn't Kawai.
是川合啊
Um.
-那个… -停
I'm good.
我不需要
I haven't said anything.
我什么都还没说
But you're about to.
看你的表情正打算说吧
Those words I absolutely hate.
我最讨厌的老套说辞
"I'm responsible as well, let's get married, I will support you.
“我也有责任 结婚吧 我来援助你
Come to Singapore with me."
跟我一起去新加坡”
No thank you, to it all.
我全部拒绝
You said everything I wanted to say.
你把我想说的话都说完了
You're so easy to read.
你的词汇就只有这种程度
Or do you already have someone?
还是说你已经有对象了？
Oh, you mean her?
哦 你说她啊？
I knew you two wouldn't last.
我就知道你们不会顺利
We were just catching up.
我们只是叙叙旧
There's no-one else.
我没有其他对象
-Then I-- -This is my child.
-那我… -这是我的孩子
I'm fine on my own.
我会一个人照顾他
-Hijiri. -Glad to see you discharged.
-小圣 -恭喜你出院
Thank you for everything. I'm sorry I made you worry.
谢谢你 很抱歉让你担心了
I'm glad you're here.
你们在这太好了
I have some news for you.
我有事要跟你们报告
AGREEMENT
（契约书）
Ms. Shioya!
老师！
It's been a long time.
好久不见了
Bullying SOS?
霸凌SOS？
It's my new work place.
是我的新工作
We provide counseling to anyone experiencing trouble at school.
我们为任何 在学校遇到困难的人提供咨询
I'm glad to see you well.
看你过得很不错 真是太好了
I ran into Kokonoe the other day.
上次我偶然遇到九重同学
He told me about your son.
我听他说了黑岩同学的事
He's still seeing Ms. Suenaga?
他跟末永老师现在还是有见面吗？
I don't plan to allow for them
我不打算让他们
to continue.
继续下去
However,
可是
sometimes I falter.
有时我会感到气馁
When I know how much
一想到会
my only son hates me.
被唯一的独生子怀恨在心
To be honest, it is tough sometimes.
老实说 有时会很难过
You aren't wrong about this.
你并没有做错
You only did what any parent would do.
这是身为父母理当做的事情
The one in the wrong,
做错的人
is Ms. Suenaga.
是末永老师
It's okay.
别担心
People always grow stronger through hardships.
经历过痛苦的人肯定会变得更加坚强
They're all precious experiences.
这全都是珍贵的经验
It's sure to help in his life ahead.
一定有助于未来的人生
THAI TRAVEL WORDS AND PHRASES
（《泰国旅游会话》）
AFTER A WHILE, HIJIRI ARRIVED.
（过没多久 小圣就来了）
I WANT TO KNOW MORE ABOUT HER. BE CLOSER TO HER.
（想更了解小圣 想更接近她）
IF ONLY I WEREN'T 15
（她说因为我才十五岁）
YOU DISAPPEARED. IT WAS THE SUMMER WHEN I WAS 15.
（后来你便从我 十五岁的夏天消失了）
Thank you very much.
谢谢光临
What is it you can do?
你能做些什么？
How will you meet her sacrifice?
对于她的付出 你能如何回报？
Hello.
你好
Think about that, Akira.
你自己想清楚 阿晶
Hello, Shotaro?
喂 胜太郎吗？
Thanks for seeing me.
抱歉 还让你来见我
It's no problem, I just have a lot of papers to fill out.
我只是有很多手续忙着要处理 没问题
You've changed.
圣 你感觉变了不少
You're no longer that reserved, over-accommodating girl.
你不再是那个含蓄 总是有所顾忌的女孩
You have yourself a goal.
你有自己的目标
It encourages me.
我也深受激励
I need to find my answer.
我需要找到自己的答案
Well, thanks for saying that.
谢谢你这么说
That encourages me in return.
这也反过来鼓励了我
How is Ms. Haraguchi?
原口小姐怎么了？
Well, I got my orders.
她给了我指令
Orders?
指令？
I'm supposed to get on here?
要我搭这个吗？
Ms. Haraguchi insisted. You know how weird she is.
原口小姐叫我一定要带你去坐 她向来有点古怪
-One please. -Okay.
-麻烦 一位 -好
Go on.
去吧
Have fun.
玩得开心点
Hello, Ms. Haraguchi?
你好 原口小姐？
Sorry, Hijiri, but I wanted your advice on something.
抱歉 小圣 但我想跟你商量一件事
Advice?
商量？
Hey.
喂
Can you see me?
你看得到我吗？
There you are.
看到了
-What did you want to talk about? -Kawai.
-要商量什么？ -川合的事
When you get to the bottom, could you tell Kawai I'm not an eccentric woman,
等你绕了一圈下来 可以帮我 转告川合 我不是古怪的女人吗？
I'm a smart woman who loves deeply
而是深情的聪明女人
and is a bit meddlesome.
偶尔很爱管闲事而已
What?
什么？
I mean,
我是说
I do something like this because I was asked to.
因为我受人之托 便想到这么做
Here.
给你
Ms. Suenaga?
老师？
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
I'm not your teacher now.
我已经不是你的老师了
Hijiri.
小圣
I wanted to
我想
see and tell you one last time.
在最后见你一面说说话
But now that I'm here, I don't know what to say.
但是真的见到面了 反而不知道该说什么
I'm panicking.
我很着急
Up until now,
直到现在
being with you made me happy,
只要跟你在一起就很幸福
and I only thought about myself.
只想到自己
But now
但现在
I want you to be happy.
我希望你能幸福
So I won't come meet you again.
所以我不会再去找你
I won't even call.
也不会联络你
But I'll always be wishing
可是我会一直祈求
for your happiness.
希望你过得幸福
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
I…
我…
I'm leaving Japan.
要离开日本了
What?
什么？
I'm going to be working abroad.
我要去国外工作
I can't believe it myself.
连自己都无法相信
I've hardly even traveled,
以前连旅行都很少去
and I'm going to some unknown place on my own.
却要独自去陌生的地方
You changed me.
是你改变了我
You are the one
是你
who gave me the strength.
给了我力量
The strength
能独自
to stand on my own.
面对未来的力量
I'm glad I met you.
能遇见你真是太好了
Goodbye.
再见
Goodbye, Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
I'm sure you'll become a good teacher.
你一定能成为好老师
Hijiri.
小圣
Good luck!
加油！
Thank you.
谢谢
Kid.
少年
Become a good man.
成为一个好男人吧
He said this wouldn't count as meeting.
他说这样就不算见到面了
You just rode on a Ferris wheel.
你只是坐了一圈摩天轮
-Thank you. -One more thing.
-谢谢你 -还有一个东西
He asked me to give you this.
他叫我转交这个给你
There you go.
给你
Mission complete?
任务完成了吗？
-Mission accomplished. -Good work, Kawai.
-任务完成 -辛苦了 川合
-I've decided. -Huh?
-我决定了 -嗯？
I'll be by your side.
我要陪在你身边
Or should I say the both of you.
还是应该说我要陪在你们身边
I didn't ask. We're done with that--
我没拜托你 这件事已经…
Sometimes, feelings aren't enough.
有时只有爱是不够的
But if there's still a chance,
不过若还有机会
I'm taking every opportunity.
我就要全力争取
So,
所以
I'll be here.
我要待在你身边
I'll succeed at work too.
我也会闯出一番事业
Even if I pass up on this position abroad.
即使我放弃了海外的这个职位
You're naive to pass up on this opportunity.
太天真了 舍弃这个机会
-But I-- -I recommended you as your boss!
-但我… -我是以上司的身份推荐了你！
I'll wait for you.
我会等你
So go become your own man,
所以你要变得能独当一面
and come home.
再回到我身边
I promise to support you in any way I can.
不管是什么形式 我都会陪着你
I hate when you say crap like that.
我真的很讨厌你的用字遣词
Why?
为什么？
-You can't do this alone. -I'm fine.
-你一个人不行 -我可以
-No, you can't.
-不 你不行的
-That's so like you. -Go to Singapore already!
-真像你会说的话 -你快点去新加坡啦！
"Ms. Suenaga.
“老师
Back then…"
当时…”
One minute of silence.
默哀一分钟
"I was a little crazy."
“我的思绪十分混乱”
Kuroiwa.
黑岩！
Did you hit your head?
你有撞到头吗？
Please! You need to stop annoying me.
拜托你不要再烦我了！
"I'd get irritated…"
“我无缘由地感到烦躁…”
I've fallen in love with you.
我喜欢上老师了
I've fallen for you!
我喜欢上你了！
"…and lose control.
“…和激动
To a point where I couldn't see myself or my surroundings.
直到完全看不见自己或周遭
That's how much…"
我就是如此地…”
I don't care what anyone says.
我不在意别人怎么说
I love you.
我喜欢老师
"I loved you."
“喜欢你”
Ms. Suenaga! Hijiri!
老师！小圣！
Don't go, Hijiri!
不要走 小圣！
Hijiri!
小圣！
I'll do my best too.
我也会加油
"December 2018.
“2018年12月
May Hijiri
希望小圣
have a happy life full of smiles.
能一直展露微笑地生活
Akira Kuroiwa."
黑岩晶”
Akira!
阿晶
-You have your test slip? -Yes.
-准考证带了吗？ -带了
Hold on, let me do a good luck ritual.
等等 我帮你祈福
Smart, smart, aloha oe!
聪明 阿罗哈 哦！
-I bet that worked. -Yeah.
-好像很有用 -绝对有用
-I'm off. -Good luck!
-我出门了 -好 路上小心
You got this!
加油！
Wait, Akira.
等等 阿晶
Here.
这个
I don't need it.
不用了啦
Come on, it's from your father.
来吧 这是你父亲给你的
ACADEMIC ACHIEVEMENT
（学业成就）
Good luck.
路上小心
Mom.
妈妈
Thanks.
谢谢
I'm off then.
我出门了
Good luck.
加油
Hello.
你好
It's me.
是我
I'm moving to Bangkok to teach Japanese.
我现在要去曼谷教日文
I'm going to
我会在那里
start my life over.
重新努力
I'll be going now.
那我走了
Hijiri.
圣
To me, you've left our nest already.
我知道你已经离开我们的羽翼了
So
所以
I want to wish you luck.
你要自己加油
Thank you.
好
But
但是
if things are really difficult,
若真的遇到难过的事
come on home.
就回来吧
I can feed you dinner at least.
我至少还能让你好好吃顿饭
Thanks, Mom.
谢谢你 妈妈
I'll be going now.
我走了
Repeat after me.
跟我念一遍
Hello.
你好
Good evening.
晚安
Good job!
你们好棒！
MS. HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣小姐）
AGREEMENT
（契约书）
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻译：高文欣